Frederick C. Nelson Papers MS198
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Frederick C. Nelson Papers
1955 -- 2007
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
School of Engineering
Nelson, Frederick C.
MS198
1.7 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Biographical papers; Course materials; and Publications.
Custodial History
Materials donated by Nelson's wife, Delia A. Nelson, in 2012.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of biographical information, publications, and course materials and notes by and about Frederick C. Nelson. The course materials primarily consist of lecture notes and presentations that Nelson prepared for courses that he taught, such as "Applied Acoustics for Mechanical Engineers."
Biographical / Historical
Frederick C. Nelson was born on August 8, 1932 in Braintree, Massachusetts. He received a B.S. from Tufts College in 1954 and he attended Harvard University for his M.S. (1955) and Ph.D. (1961). He was an Instructor in Engineering at Tufts University from 1955 to 1957, an Assistant Professor from 1957-1964, and an Associate Professor from 1964-1971. He was made a full Professor of Mechanical Engineering in 1971 and served at the Dean of the College of Engineering from 1980 to 1994. He retired from teaching in 2007 and was awarded emeritus status. Nelson died in 2009 from a melanoma.
During his tenure as dean, Nelson modernized the engineering school and its curriculum, renovating Bray Lab for the mechanical engineers, replacing the environmental labs for the civil engineers, revamping Halligan Hall for the electrical engineers and moving the chemical engineering department into the new Science and Technology Center. He also was involved in establishing technology centers in electro-optics and biotechnology, which gave the school a national reputation in research. After he left the dean's post, alumni funded the construction of the Nelson Auditorium in Anderson Hall in his honor.
Nelson's research interests encompassed acoustics, vibration, shock mechanics, and rotordynamics, a specialized branch of applied mechanics that analyzes the behavior of rotating structures such as jet engines, automobile engines, and computer disk storage. He wrote or co-authored more than 50 articles in professional publications and was a consultant to more than a dozen companies.
He spent a semester in England at the Institute for Sound and Vibration Research at the University of Southampton, two terms in France as a visiting professor at the Institut National des Sciences Appliquées de Lyon (INSA), and one term as a research scholar at Harvard University. He established and administered the student exchange program between Tufts and INSA, which continues to this day and has resulted in more than 50 Tufts students studying engineering in France for a year.
Nelson was a fellow of the Acoustical Society of America, the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, and the American Association for the Advancement of Science. He was a recipient of the Centennial Medal of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, the King Seijong Medal of the Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, the Anniversary Medal of INSA de Lyon, the Distinguished Service Medal of Tufts University, and the Career Achievement Award of the mechanical engineering department at Tufts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Faculty papers; Teaching and learning; Engineering - Study and teaching; Physics - Study and teaching; Nelson, Frederick C.
- Biographical papers, 1971 -- 2006; MS198.001; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains resumes and awards from Fredrick Nelson.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Nelson, Frederick C. (Faculty), 1971; MS198.001.001.00001 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Resumes, 2000 -- 2006; MS198.001.001.00002 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Certificates, Awards, Recognition], 1972 -- 1998; MS198.001.001.00003 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
- Course material, 1955 -- 2004; MS198.002; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains lecture notes and course notes from Fredrick Nelson's lectures.
  - Acoustics for Mechanical Engineers Structure-Fluid Interaction, 1976; MS198.002.001.00004 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Acoustics - Lecture Notes], 2003 -- 2004; MS198.002.001.00005 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Applied Acoustics for Mechanical Engineers, 1986; MS198.002.001.00006 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Lecture Notes on Waves and Acoustics], 1986; MS198.002.001.00007 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - The Industrial Revolution, 1998 -- 2001; MS198.002.001.00008 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Notes for a course on noise control, 1996 -- 2003; MS198.002.001.00009 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Noise and Vibration Control - Lecture Notes], 1986 -- 1997; MS198.002.001.00010 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - EN-28-ME Sound and Society, 2002; MS198.002.001.00011 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - EN-28 Sound and Society, 2003; MS198.002.001.00012 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Sound Power Using Intensity Meters, 2002; MS198.002.001.00013 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Lecture Notes on Sound, Vibration and Acoustics], 1997; MS198.002.001.00014 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [Lecture Notes on Green's Function], 1986; MS198.002.001.00015 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - LaGrange's Equations, 1986; MS198.002.001.00016 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - The General Theory of the Wave Equation (without derivations but with rigor), 1986; MS198.002.001.00017 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - [A Social History of Engineering - Photocopy], 2003; MS198.002.001.00018 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - ES-7 Lecture Notes, 2002; MS198.002.001.00019 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Sound and the Environment: The Case of Road Traffic Noise [Lecture Notes], 1997; MS198.002.001.00020 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Sound and Society Acoustics [Course Notes], 2004; MS198.002.001.00021 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
  - Physical Mechanics - Physics 151 Tufts; Classical Mechanics - Physics 208 Harvard [Course Notes], 1955; MS198.002.001.00022 (Box MS198 Shared 1)
- Publications, 1962 -- 2007; MS198.003; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains publications by and about Fredrick Nelson.
  - Damping of Low Frequency Vibration by Constrained Viscoelastic Layers [manuscript copy], 1967; MS198.003.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Damping of Low Frequency Vibration by Constrained Viscoelastic Layers, 1967; MS198.003.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - The Shock and Vibration Bulletin Part 3 - Isolation and Damping, Vibration Test Criteria, and Vibration Analysis and Test, 1987; MS198.003.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Journal - American Institute of Steel Construction, 1968-04; MS198.003.002.00004 (Box 2)
    Volume, issue
    5, 2
  - Sound and Vibration - Machinery Reliability, 2002; MS198.003.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Shock and Vibration, 1996; MS198.003.002.00006 (Box 2)
    3, 6
  - Journal Of Engineering for Gas Turbines and Power, 1998; MS198.003.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - A Guide to Polymers and Their Use for Vibration Isolation, 1992 -- 1994; MS198.003.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Techniques for the Design of Highly Damped Structures, 1975; MS198.003.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - On the Incorporation of Damping in Large, General-Purpose Computer Programs, 1975; MS198.003.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Damping in Joints of Built up Structures, 1975; MS198.003.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Techniques for the Design of Highly damped Structures [Manuscript copy and reprints], 1977; MS198.003.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - The Forced Vibration of a Damped Circular Ring Segment, 1973; MS198.003.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - The Forced Vibration of a Three-Layer Damped Circular Ring, 1977; MS198.003.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - Damped Vibration Theory: A State-of-the-Art Assessment, 1977; MS198.003.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - The Forced Vibration of a Damped Circular Ring Segment: Test v. Theory, 1978; MS198.003.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Damping PCBs with Foam Plastic, 1979; MS198.003.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - A Review of the Substructure Analysis of Vibrating Systems, 1979; MS198.003.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Modal Response of Shallow Circular Rings [Manuscript Copy], 1969; MS198.003.002.00019 (Box 2)
  - Constrained Layer Damping of Flat and Curved Structures, 1980; MS198.003.002.00020 (Box 2)
  - The Shock and Vibration Bulletin 51 Part 2 Environmental Testing, Shock Testing, Shock Analysis [Reprint], 1981; MS198.003.002.00021 (Box 2)
  - Understanding Government Regulation of In-Plant Noise, 1973; MS198.003.002.00022 (Box 2)
  - Shock and Seismic Excitation of Mechanical Equipment, 1974; MS198.003.002.00023 (Box 2)
  - Sound and Vibration, 1974-10; MS198.003.002.00024 (Box 2)
    8, 10
  - The Role of Closely Spaced Modes in the Seismic Response of Equipment and Structures, 1975; MS198.003.002.00025 (Box 2)
  - Visco. Layers in B'L'Gs A.I.S.E. Journal April 1968, MS198.003.002.00026 (Box 2)
  - Const. [Constrained] Layer with Partial Coverage S&V Bull [Shock and Vibration Bulletin] Nov 1968, MS198.003.002.00027 (Box 2)
  - Dis. To Low Freq. [Frequency] VIB [Vibration]. Problem Institute of Mechanical Engineers 1968, MS198.003.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Heating in Const. [Constrained] Visoelastic Layers - ASME - April 1969 - B.J. Korites, 1968; MS198.003.002.00029 (Box 2)
  - Dis. to Struct. Damp. [Structural Dampers] Struct. Div. ASCE [Journal of the Structural Division Proceedings of the American Society of Engineers] Feb 1970, MS198.003.002.00030 (Box 2)
  - F, Ao & 3: Effects Human Awareness ASME 71-VIBR-44 [The Relationship Among Frequency, Amplitude, Damping and Human Awareness for Floor Vibration Due to Impact], 1971; MS198.003.002.00031 (Box 2)
  - Damping of a Circular Ring Segment by a Constrained Viscoelastic Layer, 1970; MS198.003.002.00032 (Box 2)
  - Foam Fracture Nelson and Graves, 1972; MS198.003.002.00033 (Box 2)
  - Nonlinear Ring Nelson and NG, 1973; MS198.003.002.00034 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Noise Control and the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970, 1972; MS198.003.002.00035 (Box 2)
  - Out of Plane Vibration of a Clamped Circular Ring Segment, 1963; MS198.003.002.00036 (Box 2)
  - Out of Plane Vibration of a Clamped Circular Ring Segment, 1963; MS198.003.002.00037 (Box 2)
  - Vibration Analysis and Test Techniques, 1965; MS198.003.002.00038 (Box 2)
  - Frequency Cross-Over of Simply Supported Circular Ring Segments, 1964; MS198.003.002.00039 (Box 2)
  - Bulletin of Mechanical Engineering Education - Letter to the Editor - A Theorem Concerning Quasistatic Processes in Thermodynamics, 1964; MS198.003.002.00040 (Box 2)
  - Resonant Beam S/V Bull Apr. 1966 [Shock and Vibration Bulletin], MS198.003.002.00041 (Box 2)
  - Polyurethane Foam SME 66 WA/RP-3 Nov. '66, 1966; MS198.003.002.00043 (Box 2)
  - The Use of Viscoelastic Material to Damp Vibration in Buildings and Large Structures, 1968; MS198.003.002.00045 (Box 2)
  - Vibration of Circular Ring Segments [Doctoral Thesis], 1967; MS198.003.002.00046 (Box 2)
  - [Who's Who Among America's Teachers Form], 1998; MS198.003.002.00047 (Box 2)
  - Noise Control Engineering Journal, 2001; MS198.003.002.00048 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Noise Abatement and the Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970, 1975; MS198.003.002.00049 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Noise Measurement, 1998; MS198.003.002.00050 (Box 2)
  - Guide on Evaluation and Abatement of Traffic Noise, 1993; MS198.003.002.00051 (Box 2)
  - Sound and Society [Originals], 1996; MS198.003.002.00052 (Box 2)
  - Environmental Noise Measurements - Technical Review, 1986; MS198.003.002.00053 (Box 2)
  - The Equivalent Sound Level, 1996; MS198.003.002.00054 (Box 2)
  - Sound Power Measurements Application Note 1230, 1992; MS198.003.002.00055 (Box 2)
  - American National Standard - Method for the Physical Measurement of Sound, 1962; MS198.003.002.00056 (Box 2)
  - Principles of Vibration and Measurement Analysis, 2002; MS198.003.002.00057 (Box 2)
  - Acoustics Today, 2006; MS198.003.002.00058 (Box 2)
    2, 4
  - Acoustics Today, 2007; MS198.003.002.00059 (Box 2)
    3, 2
  - Acoustics Today, 2007; MS198.003.002.00060 (Box 2)
    3, 3